Guide to the Albert Lasker Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Albert Lasker Papers,
1928-1952
(bulk dates 1946-1952).
Lasker, Albert Davis, 1880-1952.
4.62 linear ft. (11 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
6906282
MS#1460
Albert Lasker (1880-1952) is best known as an advertising executive and philanthropist. His papers contain personal and business correspondence, as well as material related to Lasker's activities and interests, particularly with regard to medicine and public health issues.
Biographical Note
Albert Davis Lasker was born in Freiberg, Germany, on May 1, 1880, but was raised in Galveston, Texas. He was the third child of Morris Lasker, an investor and banker, and Nettie Davis Lasker.
Lasker was initially interested in journalism, and worked as a newspaper reporter during his teens. His father disapproved of this career, and in 1898 secured a position for him at Lord & Thomas, an advertising firm in Chicago. Lasker rose quickly at Lord & Thomas, becoming a partner in 1903, and sole owner within the next decade. He ultimately sold the firm to his partners and retired from active business at the end of 1942. Considered a pioneer in modern advertising, the firm's clients included Kotex, Lucky Strike, Pepsodent, Kleenex, Palmolive, Studebaker, Sunkist, RCA, and Frigidaire.
Lasker's interests were not limited to the world of advertising. From 1916-1925, he was part owner of the Chicago Cubs. Indeed, the Lasker plan for the reorganization of baseball after the 1919 "Black Sox" scandal paved the way for the election of the sport's first commissioner in 1920. He also supported the University of Chicago. He donated his private golf course to the university, and also gave one million dollars to establish the Lasker Foundation for Medical Research in 1928. He served as a trustee of the university from 1937-1942.
In addition to sports and education, Lasker also had an interest in politics that spanned some 34 years. Although he was a Republican, he served in both Republican and Democratic administrations. In 1917, he served as a special assistant to the Secretary of Agriculture under President Woodrow Wilson. He served as an Assistant to the Chairman of the National Republican Committee from 1918-1920, and worked on the campaign and election of President Warren Harding. He then served as the Chair of the United States Shipping Board from 1920-1923. Later, he was a floor leader for the Illinois delegation to the Republican National Convention in 1940.
Concerned with Jewish affairs on both a local and national level in the early 1940s, Lasker was the director of the Jewish Charities of Chicago and a member of the executive board of the American Jewish Committee. In memory of his father, who had an interest in agriculture for Jews, Lasker and other family members purchased farming land in Pennsylvania that allowed for the training of poor Jewish immigrants in agriculture. He also donated to Hadassah and other organizations. In 1950, he and his wife made a trip to Israel, which he described as the highlight of his life.
A renowned philanthropist, Lasker founded the Albert and Mary Lasker Foundation with his wife in 1942, dedicated to the support of biomedical research for curing disease and improving human life. The foundation presents annual awards recognizing those who have made major advances in the understanding, diagnosis, treatment, cure, and prevention of human disease. The awards are considered to be among the most prestigious in medical science. In 1944, Lasker was the primary force behind a fundraising drive to increase the money spent on cancer research in the United States. He was also interested in federal involvement in medical issues, and was involved in efforts to create national health insurance and a national fund for medical education during the Truman administration.
Lasker died of cancer on May 30, 1952, in New York City.
Scope and Content
Albert Lasker is best known as an advertising executive and philanthropist. His papers consist primarily of correspondence and subject files from the last five years of his life. During these years, he experienced bouts of ill health that forced him to restrict his activities for extended periods. His papers do document his interests and philanthropic work in medicine, particularly as related to cancer and proposals for national health insurance and a national medical education fund. There is also some material related to the Lasker Foundation for Medical Research at the University of Chicago.
The collection includes a small amount of personal material, including appointment books, biographical information, clippings, contribution information, and mailing lists.
There is necessarily overlap between Albert Lasker's papers and the more extensive papers of his wife, Mary Lasker, whom he married in 1940. Additional information on the couple's philanthropic work is filed with her papers.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1928-1952
Series II: Subject Files, 1933-1952
Subjects
Committee for the Nation's Health.; National Fund for Medical Education (U.S.); University of Chicago--Lasker Foundation for Medical Research.; Lasker, Albert Davis, 1880-1952.; Lasker, Mary.; National health insurance--Law and legislation--United States.; Philanthropists--United States.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions. This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Lasker, Mary Gift 1995
Bequest of Mary Lasker, 1995
Selected Related Material-- at Columbia
Reminiscences of Albert Davis Lasker, Oral History Research Office
Mary Lasker Papers, 1940-1993 Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Reminiscences of Mary Lasker: oral history, 1965 Oral History Research Office
Reminiscences of Mary Lasker: oral history, 1982 Oral History Research Office
- Series I: Correspondence, 1928-1952
  Lasker's correspondence files include personal and business correspondence on both unique and routine matters. The files include correspondence handled by both Lasker and his secretary. Notable correspondents include Claude Pepper, David Sarnoff, and Major Alexander P. de Seversky.
  - A--General, 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - B--General, 1947-1951 (Box 1, Folder 2 to 3)
  - C--General, 1947-1951, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 4 to 5)
  - Cale, Ruth, 1946-1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - D--General, 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - E--General, 1947-1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - European File, 1949, 1951, (2 Folders); (Correspondence received by the Laskers while on vacation) (Box 2, Folder 2 to 3)
  - Ewing, Oscar R., 1950 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - F--General, 1950-1952, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 5 to 6)
  - G--General, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Gimbel, Bernard, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Golden, John, 1950-1952, (includes John Gunther) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - H--General
    - 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1949-1951 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Harvard, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Health Insurance, 1947, (Re: National Health Insurance bills) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - I--General, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - J--General, 1949-1951 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - K--General, 1949-1951 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - L--General, 1949-1951 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Lasker Foundation for Medical Research--University of Chicago, 1928, (2 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 8 to 9)
  - Lord & Thomas, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - M--General, 1947-1951, (4 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 1 to 4)
  - Madison File, 1951, (Correspondence with the University of Wisconsin regarding an honorary degree for Mary Lasker) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Mahler, Ernst, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Mc General, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Meyer, Andre, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Murray, Senator James E., 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - N--General, 1949-1951 (Box 5, Folder 1 to 2)
  - O--General, 1949-1951 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Oughterson, Dr. A.W., 1946 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - P General, 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Patterson, Chat, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Pepper, Senator Claude, 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Q--General, 1948-1952, (Joint Queensview Housing Enterprise) (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - R General, 1949-1952, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 9 to 10)
  - Rosensohn & Family, Mrs. Samuel, 1951-1952, (Lasker's sister) (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - S--General, 1949-1952, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 1 to 2)
  - Sarnoff, David, 1950-1951, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 3 to 4)
  - Selz, A.K., 1950-1952 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Seversky, Major Alexander P. de, 1947-1951 (Box 6, Folder 6 to 7)
  - Simon & Schuster, 1950-1951 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Spies, Dr. Tom, 1950-1951 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - T--General, 1947-1951 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - U--General, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - V--General, 1949-1952 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - W--General, 1948-1952, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 1 to 2)
  - X-Y--General, 1950-1952 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Z--General, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1933-1952
  This series contains subject files documenting Lasker's activities and interests. Most of these files are related to medicine, and include material on cancer, the Committee for the Nation’s Health, the Lasker Foundation for Medical Research at the University of Chicago, the National Fund for Medical Education, Michael Reese Hospital, and legislation on national health insurance (1947-1950). The series also includes a small amount of personal material, including appointment books, biographical information, clippings, contribution information, and mailing lists.
  - American Committee for a United Europe, 1949-1950 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - American Jewish Committee, 1947-1951 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Appointments, 1947 January-1948 January, 1950 1951 April-1952 January, (3 Folders) (Box 7)
  - Arthritis, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Atomic Information, 1946-1947, (Includes correspondence with Albert Einstein) (Folder 8)
  - Cancer
    - Adams, John, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - American Cancer Society, 1946-1947, 1949-1952, (3 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 2 to 4)
    - Memo of Interview with Mr. Jacobi in Re: Cancer, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - New York Cancer Committee, 1949-1952, (2 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 6 to 7)
  - Committee for the Nation's Health, (includes correspondence with Chat Patterson)
    - 1949 January-June (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - 1949 July-December (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Contributions (Given), 1949 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Contributions (Foundation) Given, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Cortisone, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Friends of Democracy, 1947-1951, (4 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 5 to 8)
  - Health Insurance
    - Testimony on National Health Insurance Bills, 1947 July 11, (3 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 9 to 11)
    - 1949 January-June, (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 12 to 13)
    - 1949 July-December (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Lasker, Albert D. Testimony on National Health Insurance Bills, 1947 July 11 & 1949 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - 1950 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - National Health Bill (Speeches, Articles, Etc.), 1947-1948, Undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Bills, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Jewish Affairs--Organizations, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Lasker, Albert D.
    - Clippings, 1950-1952 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Personal, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Trustee, 1947-1950 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Lasker Foundation for Medical Research (University of Chicago), 1933-1937, 1949-1951 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Luckman, Charles, 1946-1950 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Mailing Lists, 1951-1952, Undated, (Lists for Christmas cards, thank-you notes, etc.) (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - The Marshall Plan, 1947-1948 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Medical Education, 1948-1950 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Medical Research--General, 1928-1952 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Michael Reese Hospital
    - The Psychiatric and Psychosomatic Institute, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - 1945, 1949-1950 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Motion Pictures, 1946-1952 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - The Nation, 1949-1950 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - National Broadcasting Company (NBC)--Niles Trammell/John Royal, 1950-1952 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - National Committee on Housing, Inc., 1948-1949 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - National Foundation for Medical Education, 1949-1952, (2 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 8 to 9)
  - New School of Social Research, 1948-1949 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Public Affairs Expense, 1949 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Theatrical Productions, 1949-1951 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Travel, 1951 (Box 11, Folder 13)